This video is sponsored by Storyblocks.
Get unlimited stock media downloads at
one set price using my link in the
description.
We tend to view the mind as something
that produces things. Thoughts,
concepts, perceptions. In a relative
sense, this may be true. But perhaps in
a deeper, more accurate sense, it is
actually the opposite that is true.
Rather than producing, perhaps the mind
is primarily reducing. [music]
That is, it's taking the vast ocean of
potential mental awareness and ability,
a capacity to grasp and interface with
reality as it is in full unadulterated
form and filtering it into a tiny narrow
[music] trickle like a water pressure
reducing valve turned almost all the way
down. Consciousness would thus not
really be the source of mental phenomena
or the access [music] point to reality,
but rather it would be the filter that
largely keeps us from these [music]
things. In the words of writer and
philosopher Aldus Huxley referring to
the full potentiality of the mind using
the term mind at large he writes [music]
in so far as we are animals our business
is at all costs to survive to make
biological survival possible mind at
large has to be funneled through the
reducing valve of the brain and nervous
system. What comes out at the other end
is a measly trickle of the kind of
consciousness [music] which will help us
to stay alive on the surface of this
particular planet.
Huxley is most widely known for his
fiction novels, his most famous being by
far Brave New World. However, throughout
his life, he also published many
profound works of non-fiction and
philosophy. Though they are often
overshadowed by his novels, his
non-fiction works are deeply profound
and continue to impact various fields of
philosophy, mystical studies, social
criticism, and wider [music]
conversations around consciousness. with
what seems to have been a heightened
perceptiveness of both the exterior
world, society, science, technology, and
politics, as well as the interior world,
ontology, metaphysics, consciousness,
and mysticism. Huxley's literary
explorations and philosophical insights
extend in nearly every direction, out
and in, past, present, and future,
material and ethereal.
In the realm of philosophy and
mysticism, one of Huxley's most notable
contributions is popularizing a unique
school of [music] thought known as
perennialism. The origins of
perennialism go as far back as
prehistoric shamanic traditions with
early expressions and practices [music]
revealing the fundamental intuition at
the core of the philosophy. However, in
terms of a school of thought, it only
properly took form during the
Renaissance and early modern periods
with philosophers like Marcilio Pacino
and Godfrieded Vilheim Linets
spearheading its development. Not only
does perennialism go back into deep
history, but it also spans across the
entire globe with touchstones in
countless philosophies, ideologies, and
religions. This vastness is possible
because perennialism central doctrine is
that there is a timeless wisdom that is
accessible to all humans and universal
to all philosophical and mystical
traditions. Perennialism's primary focus
is on the examination and synthesis of
the truths and wisdoms that seem to
surface independently across time and
place which share remarkably similar
metaphors, interpretations or insights
despite having never been in [music]
contact. In perennialist thought, these
consistent truths are referred to as
philosophia pennis. Though it should be
noted that there is much debate
surrounding the significance and
validity of the overlapping nature of
these truths, and there is no consensus
on the precise meaning of philosophia
pennis. Discussing the term historian of
philosophy Charles B. Schmidt writes,
"Although there is no agreement on the
precise meaning of the phrase, it is
usually taken to indicate that some sort
of continuous theme runs throughout the
history of philosophy, that certain
enduring and lasting truths are
recognizable in the philosophical
writings of all historical periods.
Philosophia Prenis is a philosophy which
endures. Its truth is [music] considered
to persist from generation to generation
long after ephemeral philosophical fads
and fashions [music] come and go.
Potential examples of philosophia pennis
are not especially hard to find though
they are rarely simple or literal. In
his book the perennial philosophy
published in 1945. Huxley draws
parallels between eastern and western
mystics [music] from the upupanads to
meister ehart. Though the equivalences
he makes are often interpretive rather
than literal, he attempts to explore and
synthesize the underlying ontological
and moral principles shared by
humanity's various traditions.
Perennialists [music]
like Huxley argue that these significant
overlaps reveal an underlying unchanging
metaphysical reality. Huxley explains
philosophia pennis as the metaphysic
that recognizes a divine reality
substantial to the [music] world of
things and lives and minds. The
psychology that finds in the soul
something similar to or even identical
with divine reality. The ethic that
places man's final end in the knowledge
of the imminent and transcendent ground
of all being. The thing is immemorial
and universal.
Whether these universals truly point to
a timeless metaphysical reality or are
just expressions of the tendencies of
the human brain and physiology which
have remained largely unchanged over the
course of human evolution is up for
debate. It is possible that these
similar ideas, metaphors, insights, and
interpretations are no different than
the similarities between weapons, like
spears and clubs, and table wear like
bowls and spoons, found across different
times and places in human history,
despite having never contacted or
influenced each other. Like spears and
spoons, these truths and insights could
merely be the manifestations of the
commonalities of the brain, interfacing
with the commonalities of the world.
imprints and filters of the mind
pressing out the same shapes and designs
made by and for the world.
Regardless of any metaphysical truth,
the vast apparent consistencies across
mystic and philosophical traditions are
certainly profound. At the very least,
it signifies a potential realm of ideas,
insights, [music] and wisdom that appear
extraordinarily robust. intersubjective
truths and perhaps even objective truths
that seem immune to the oscillations of
[music] the world and civilization to
progress, science, technology, scale and
awareness as well as their counterparts.
For Huxley, however, as a self-described
perennialist, there is a single unified
eternal [music] divine reality that
underpins everything. And crucially,
this realm is accessible. There are
methods of contemplation and modes of
altered consciousness that [music]
according to him can open the doors of
the mind or the valves and reveal the
perennial truth. The problem however and
why we can't ordinarily tap into this
realm of reality according to Huxley
lies in the way our consciousness is
mediated by the brain. We cannot use our
ordinary consciousness to access this
higher realm because that very
consciousness is what fails it.
Huxley's long-standing fascination with
the mind was only further enhanced after
taking a dose of measculine, a
psychedelic compound found in certain
cacti, which he took under the
supervision of a psychiatrist in [music]
1953. This experience along with other
psychedelic experiences he underwent
seemed to him to unveil his normal
consciousness and loosen the filtering
functions of the brain. The results
revealed to him what he described as
reality in a fuller, unmediated,
boundaryless form. Referring to one of
his experiences, he writes, "I was
sitting in my study, looking intently at
a small glass vase. The vase contained
only three flowers. I had been struck by
the lively dissonance of its colors, but
that was no longer the point. I was not
looking now at an unusual flower
arrangement. I was seeing what Adam had
seen on the morning of his creation, the
miracle moment by moment of naked
existence."
Huxley would go on to express what he
formed as his theory of the mind in his
[music] essays the doors of perception
published in 1954 and heaven and hell
published in 1956.
Drawing on the theories of philosophers
Cidi Broad and Henri Burkon Huxley
argues that the mind's primary function
as mediated by the brain and nervous
system is to reduce potential awareness
not increase it. In the words of CD
broad which Huxley cites directly the
function of the brain and nervous system
and sense [music] organs is in the main
eliminative and not productive. Each
person is at each moment capable of
remembering all that has ever happened
to him and of perceiving everything that
is happening everywhere in the universe.
The function of the brain and nervous
system is to protect us from being
overwhelmed [music] and confused by this
mass of largely useless and irrelevant
knowledge by shutting out most of what
we should otherwise perceive or remember
at any moment and leaving only that very
small and special selection which is
likely to be practically useful.
According to this view, the brain works
to filter and reduce a sort of ocean of
reality into little drips of experiences
and thoughts [music] primarily in the
form of symbols and concepts so that we
can interface with the world more
effectively and efficiently. It is
merely an evolutionary process doing its
job. And what we are left with, as
Huxley put it, is a measly trickle of
consciousness. We taste [music] test the
droplets of the mystical oneness of all
things, our thirst remaining forever
unquenched.
Huxley argues, however, that through
certain forms of inner experience and
contemplation, [music] like meditation,
prayer, aesthetic observation or
mystical engagement, particularly that
of spiritual, [music] religious,
philosophical, or psychedelic nature, we
can open up the valve of our [music]
consciousness, and let in a more
substantial flow, seeing reality for
what it is, [music] or what he referred
to as the suchness of reality. In doing
so, we obtain an awareness beyond
awareness, [music] beyond thoughts,
beyond symbols, beyond concepts. Objects
cease to be objects. The boundaries of
the plural world dissolve. Time folds in
on itself. Nothing becomes knowable in
the sense that everything becomes
knowable. Huxley writes, "To be shaken
out of the ruts of ordinary perception,
to be shown for a [music] few timeless
hours the outer and inner world, not as
they appear to an animal obsessed with
survival [music]
or to a human being obsessed with words
and notions, but as they are apprehended
[music] directly and unconditionally by
mind at large. This is an experience of
inestimable value to anyone.
Ultimately, regardless of what is true,
regardless of [music] the accuracy of
Huxley's theories and advocacies, and
regardless of whether perennialism
points to some fundamental nature of
reality, all these ideas and reflections
are extremely intriguing and [music]
important. They remind us that there is
always something beneath the surface
that we all share but can't quite know
or put our finger on. Aquafers of
possibility and potential revelation
that, even if only for brief moments,
can [music] be tapped into and tasted.
These possibilities compel us to
question the very nature and
malleability of our minds and its
relationship [music] with the world. And
perhaps most importantly, if we follow
the train of thought conducted by
Huxley, we might arrive somewhere in the
vicinity of some kind of enlightenment,
as he referred to it, an increasing
dissolvement of the self [music] and a
greater embrace of the suchness of
reality as it is in full form, its
apparent goodness [music] and badness,
pain and pleasure, beauty and ugliness.
In the words of Huxley, to be
enlightened is to be aware always of
total reality and its imminent
otherness. To be aware of it and yet
remain in a condition to survive as an
animal. Our goal is to discover that we
have always been where we ought to be.
These reflections about the mind,
perception, and the strangeness [music]
of being are central to my upcoming
book, The Terrible Paradox of
Self-awareness. It comes out March 2026
and is available for pre-order now. And
on that note, there is at least one
other mode of experience that can offer
mind-opening, consciousness altering
effects. One that Huxley never
explicitly mentioned, though he alluded
to it, creativity. In this video
sponsor, Storyblocks makes engaging in
and tapping into the creative process
profoundly accessible and versatile.
Fundamentally, Storyblocks is a platform
that offers unlimited access to
high-quality stock videos, images,
music, sound [music] effects, and more.
Effectively, however, it turns the world
of images, videos, templates, and audio
into an everexpanding digital collage
studio, constantly refreshed and added
to which you can pull from and piece
different assets together, creating
wholly novel artworks or supplementing
your existing work. Whether it's a short
film that needs B-roll, an After Effects
animation that needs a foundation, a
YouTube video that needs sound effects,
or a project that needs essentially
everything besides your vision. The best
part, unlike other traditional stock
platforms, Story Blocks uses an
unlimited model where you can download
as much as you want for one consistent
subscription price. That means if you
don't end up using something, it doesn't
cost you anything. And everything is
created by real artists who agree to
share their work. 100% royalty-free,
pre-licicensed, and ready [music] to
use, so you can be confident you're
incorporating everything ethically and
legally. Personally, I can't speak
highly enough of Story Blocks, both on
and off the channel. It's continued to
make bringing visions to life
streamlined, professional, and most
importantly, exciting, and unrestrained.
To get started with unlimited stock
media downloads at one set price, head
to storyblocks.com/under
or click the link in the description.
And of course, [music] as always, thank
you so much for watching in general and
see you next video.